howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show
[Music]
listeners have asked us to provide
pointers some of the resources we talked
about on the show we now have links to
books and articles referenced in recent
podcasts that are available on our
website
we also offer full transcripts go to gym
rut show calm
that's gym rut show calm today's guest
is Michelle Bauwens Michelle is the
founder and vision coordinator of the
p2p foundation and works in
collaboration with a global group of
researchers in the exploration of peer
production governance and property cool
title Michelle what is a vision
coordinator well the way we were
organized is that we had five streams of
activity so one was visioning then we
had communication operational forgot the
two of us well but anyway so each the
ideas that each of these streams is kind
of you know relatively autonomous and so
we had a little extra budget last year
so we divided equally over the five
groups and then they kind of decided
themselves how to spend it and so
basically what I do is on the one hand
I'm kind of a librarian so I spend quite
a substantial amount of time what I call
curating which means you know what is
happening and so I try to then the
second step for me is to make sense of
it right so I kind of come into theory
in that sense so how can I make sense in
an integrated way what's the kind of
largest narrative I can make or what I
see that gives certain coherence to what
I'm seeing and you know it's a bit
related to that idea of Ken Wilber when
he talks about vision logic right so
it's just something that I do naturally
organically I'm a big picture person so
I like you know macro history I like to
put things together and I've also been
librarian for you know almost all my
life so putting these two together these
two aspects together is a bit second
nature for me
that sounds like a great job certainly
it certainly beats being a CEO all right
I've been that a few times that's a pain
in the ass right so let's start with p2p
which for our audience stands for peer
to peer you can find a lot more here at
the p2p Foundation dotnet and as usual
we'll have links to everything we talk
about every organization every book and
most articles on the episode page at Jim
Rutte show com so feel free to go there
and get the link to these things so
let's start with at the simplest level a
simple syllable description will dig
into considerable detail but what is
peer to peer what does that mean all
right so I'll first give you a short
explanation but I do want to give some
historical background why this is
important so peer to peer was used you
know about 15 years ago I think when
Napster came out and so the idea was
that we could have computer systems
where every computer was autonomous and
could freely communicate with other
computers without passing through a
server it's kind of like the founding
principle of the internet if you like
and it it has changed it's become more
hierarchical as is these big companies
took it over but originally the idea you
know the people who invented the
internet was to make it a peer-to-peer
system now if you take that idea and
apply it to people then you have really
the same dynamic so what if we had a
system where every person could freely
communicate self-organized and you know
make projects with any other person
freely without any intermediaries or
gatekeepers and so that's the definition
right so any system where any individual
can connect organize and even produce
value together on this basis of free
contribution would be a peer-to-peer
system but I want to give you some
historical idea because for me it's a
kind of anthropological revolution now I
want to explain why that is so when we
started the human adventure you know in
the Neolithic times most people live in
small groups and there is this idea from
a
apologies called Dunbar that like
primates people can remember and trust
about 150 people so imagine you live in
a tribe in a village you know nomadic
group and you know everybody's skin is
skin with you is family uncles and you
know whatever and so whenever there is
an issue you just you know you go talk
to them basically so it's easy to solve
problems in a convivial way but as soon
as we kind of got scale in your society
you know and had larger groups that that
didn't work anymore so we kind of also
had to invent a hierarchy you know in
terms of streamlining communication and
transaction costs in in society and what
that then creates is a conundrum because
people what they love most is to live in
family be with friends and have this
convivial lifestyle but in order to
exist and compete with other you know
predatory and competing entities then
the hierarchy will impose very strict
limits of what can be done so in this
kind of context and which we know 5,000
years of class-based society is behind
us the fact that we invented technology
that allows people to virtually connect
with each other and actually coordinate
on a global scale
you know like Linux or Wikipedia right
so tons of people are collaborating and
yet the average team level of a Linux
you know group is four people so what
that tells me is that you can have
another form of conviviality which can
then coexist with our territorial
organization and so that's kind of the
promise of peer-to-peer is that you know
we can organize ourselves around common
projects and because you and I will be
contributing out of a free Accord that
means a lot of things in terms of
organization because why should I listen
to you tell me what I should do if we
both freely contributing to this project
so we will have to invent other ways of
working together and so that's where the
other words come from so you have peer
production the capacity to freely
produce together
you have peer governance the capacity to
govern this collaboration and pproperty
the capacity to create you know mutual
pools of knowledge and resources which
can help us work together so that's kind
of in a nutshell why I like peer-to-peer
very good we recently had on the show
rich Bartlett from Inspiral and he
talked a lot about the self-organizing
aspects of it and for people that are
interested in that I'd recommend they go
check out that episode as well closely
related now that you mention it one of
things I think is probably useful for
our audience and probably for both of us
to get on the same page is that when
people think of peer-to-peer jour
naively in the current world they mostly
think about non rival risks goods things
like open-source software or a music
file back in the Napster days that could
be copied for a tiny fraction of a said
but economics can in one cut on the
world of goods is into rival RIS and
nonrival wrists my favorite example for
rival wrists is a ham sandwich either
you eat it or I eat it we can't both eat
it right we could cut it down the middle
but it's essentially a non rival or as
good once it's been eaten whoever ate it
has done the job on the other hand and
nonrival risk good is a good that can be
reproduced very inexpensively like a
music file or most medicines actually
are very inexpensive to make so that if
it weren't entangled with intellectual
property constraints there would be no
reason that everyone who wanted it could
have it
there's third class so-called public
goods you know for instance law and
order as a public good we all take part
in it for both good and evil as it's
turning out I suspect but in terms of
exchange and more traditional economics
rival risks and nonrival risks are
important divisions can you speak a
little bit to the applicability of the
peer-to-peer idea in the rival risk
domain in particular where I think
people are less used to hearing about it
yes so I actually want to tell you first
that peer-to-peer can be used in a
market
exchange and some people would argue
that the market is a kind of a
peer-to-peer system because you know
peers can exchange and now of course we
have these platforms that are privately
owned but where people can exchange like
supply and demand can meet each other on
a platform the kind of peer-to-peer I
use is more in the sense of your
question so it's using these
peer-to-peer dynamics to create Commons
and actually I'm going to kind of
disagree with you because the the first
Commons and a commons is defined within
three ways so it's a shared resource
that is produced or maintained by a
community or a group of stakeholders and
that is self regulated so these so it's
a resource it's a group of people and
it's a form of governance and that's how
Elinor Ostrom who kind of was the first
to really study the Commons defined it
broadly and if you look at the history
of the Commons the first comments were
actually you know physical resources so
if you look at forests and river basins
and fishing communities you know before
we had a capitalist system most of these
resources where it comes so for example
if you travel in Japan or Austria and
Switzerland and you ask yourself why is
everything so green you know in the in
the mountain flanks of these countries
is because they are Commons in other
words the villages themselves are the
ones that manage the use of that
resource and they do so with a long-term
perspective so because they all depend
on it they will manage it collectively
in a way that you know seven generations
can can still use it so that's the first
phase of the Commons and I want to give
you a historical example you know the
most important Catholic ritual in
medieval Europe next to Christmas and
Easter was called the Rogan tied
procession and this was when the all the
people of the parish would collectively
you know circumvent it's called
perambulation I think in English city
would go around the parish and come
their comments they would say this is
from all of us so this is important but
it means that in the Middle Ages if you
were a farmer in a parish your identity
was actually constituted by your
collaboration in these comments so
here's of course on the one hand you the
feudal system you so you had a bit of
land on your own you had the land of the
Lord which you you know you worked and
gave part of it to the Lord in in
exchange for protection but you also had
these common resources that you could
use so that's the first phase and
capitalism whatever you think of it as a
system is really based on the
destruction of the Commons so this is
called the enclosures right it's when
people started fencing in and what you
have to remember that the originally
property was not absolute individual
property but in this context it was
something that belonged to your family
and as the head as a patriarch you know
of your family lineage you couldn't do
what you want with the property you have
to protect it for all the descendants
that would come after you but once you
have property that you can sell whenever
you want that's when the enclosure
started because what people then found
was that was that they could make more
profit with sheep done with people and
the enclosures is this whole process of
fencing the common property and making
into private property so the second
phase of the Commons was social Commons
so all these farmers expelled from their
farm they become workers in the you know
early manufacturing cities like in
England in 19th century they have no
protection whatsoever they die when
they're 30 on average and so they create
the mutualization of their life risk and
this is what gave us the welfare system
you know like the New Deal type of
organizations that you have in the US
you know they weren't invented by
Roosevelt he looked at what the people
already doing and then decided to
generalize and beverage in the UK they
did the same so this is the second phase
when the social Commons became dominant
because the physical resources had been
privatized and the welfare state is the
nationalization if you like of these
social Commons are used
with me then I I am because then I go to
the third phase which is you know what
we know in our generations which is a
digital Commons and so the Internet's
kind of showed people who are no longer
familiar with what Commons were that
while we can work together we can create
a Wikipedia a free software open design
so culture II that was very important to
for people to realize that it's actually
easy to work together but we didn't stop
there Jim because the fourth phase which
I studied in Ghent in 2017 in the north
of Belgium is the urban Commons and you
know they have increased tenfold from
roughly 2006 to 2016 you can take any
city in the West with even in Latin
America and you'll see studies that show
an enormous exponential rise of urban
Commons so that means that people for
example if you want organic food are
going to create CSAs right consumer
supported agriculture community land
Trust's energy co-ops so we're actually
going back to material comments because
in many cases there is either market
failure or state failure and people who
are motivated will say okay why don't we
do it together through our resources to
make sure that we all can eat organic
food and I would say and this is I'm
concluding the the phase that we are now
is what I call Cosmo local production is
that think about permaculture right
there's thousands and thousands of plots
nowadays so they're very local but all
the people do permaculture learn from
each other in their network where they
pull the knowledge together and then you
have for example in Europe 120 what we
call multi factories where craftspeople
you know look for like if an old factory
they can use they mutual eyes the space
so each crafts person has his own space
but they they banished it together they
use open-source principles and all of
them working together work for the
invisible Factory that's how they call
it and this is everything they do
together and pull together
so there you can see that a Commons is
very much also potentially related to
the market and I would argue that the
medieval markets in the you know in the
three European cities of the Middle Ages
where markets that were working with the
gills which were Commons so they created
these ethical economies that would
protect the worker guilds you know
against and divide the power with the
church and the law and the feudal lords
and the kings and they succeeded this
for you know a few centuries yeah very
good in fact yeah when I was saying that
what we think of when we think of peer
to peer these days tends to be
electronic and Internet you're
absolutely right the real history of it
goes all the way back to the dawn of
time when all of our production was
essentially peer-to-peer yet the
difference is only that now because we
have virtual tools we can create virtual
territories on top of the physical
that's that's the the big revolution so
it existed that it was bounded you know
in time and space to you know smaller
communities and what we've achieved with
the internet is the potential to have
global projects that are kind of
coordinated to these comments yeah we're
going to talk about that a little later
I just add a little personal note which
I do from time to time I happen to live
in a county in the United States which
does not have the fence in law for
property that's one of the few in the
United States that still offense out law
essentially so in principle the common
still exists and there are lots of
mountains fair amount of
government-owned land that in principle
you can put your hogs out in the fall
and run on the common land and it's
legal sort of that's interesting yeah
and the law literally is still that it's
your duty to fence animals out if that's
what you want to do not everybody
understands that which produce some hurt
feelings particularly from newcomers who
don't understand this older tradition
but within US law it is legal at least
in the state of Virginia for a county to
choose to be a fence out County rather
than fence in I think there's three or
something out of
125 I'm Justin ated I want to learn more
about this I didn't know this this is an
interesting because just this week I saw
several things passing by about common
land pastures in Europe and I was
actually you know surprised that so much
of it is still existing so for example
in Galicia which is one of the Spanish
provinces one-third of the land is still
common land and in France and I didn't
expect it at all there's 100,000 people
in an association of you know kind of
communal Commons so these are like in
the Alps and the Piron a region's common
River Management common forest
management so they do still exist even
though they kind of disappeared from
from consciousness of you know most city
dwellers and everything yeah that's good
we should definitely catwalk those for
people to learn about ok let's move on
here a little bit one thing I want to
reference is that a fair amount of what
follows not all of it I dug out of a
book
Michelle wrote with the source Costas
and Alex Positas called peer to peer the
Commons manifesto if you want to dig in
a little bit deeper than we're going in
the show grab that book it's available I
got my copy on Amazon I think it's also
available for free from the p2p
foundation website and at the University
of Westminster they have like a freely
downloadable copy and Creative Commons
very good all right talking about
Creative Commons just so I think a good
very nice little swing to my next topic
one of the things you have on your
website is that part of what you're
working on is universal access
guaranteed through licenses such as
Creative Commons GPL your production
license etc do you have thoughts about
that what licenses are good for
peer-to-peer and and and creating a
Commons and you know which ones tend to
be used to exploit the process for
personal or corporate wealth any
thoughts on that yeah I'm a bit of a
heretic in that sense because so
basically today you have the choice
between kind of two extremes which is
copyright and copy left and copyright is
of course it's mine and if you want to
use
you need my permission you to pay me and
then copyleft exact opposite is
everybody can use it but my view is that
if you want to create you know better
ethical and generative markets
non-predatory markets is that you need
some defense mechanism and that's why in
the book I propose something called copy
fair which kind of sits in between so
what is copy fair is the idea that
around these productive communities
which which are open collaborative
systems where everybody can collaborate
to Linux and and about the new
blockchain systems at the same principle
but if you want to create an economy
which is not controlled by you know big
multinational corporations you have to
protect the the ethical firms and so
copy fair is the principle that the
knowledge can be shared as much as you
like but if you want to make money then
you need to show some form of
reciprocity with the community who has
produced that knowledge and so on an
example of a group that does that is the
fair shares association which is
actually a property format in the UK and
so what they do is everybody can use the
word they produce with a Creative
Commons non-commercial license which is
like a restriction but if you pay the
membership fee and so you reciprocate in
the production of that knowledge then
you have the Creative Commons license
which also allows commercial use right I
think that this is interesting and what
I am and I'm seeking some kind of
convergence between you know the co-op's
model destroy the earth economic models
the big corporations the social
entrepreneurs the not-for-profit sector
and if they would use these licenses
they could then you know create these
kind of ethical generative
entrepreneurial coalition's which I call
and trade Ontario because
entrepreneurial actually means a team
illogically taking in between and I
would like to see you know the kind of
markets that we had in medieval cities
which which in narrative markets with
issues like just pricing where you know
there is this consciousness also in the
market players
that they're there to serve society yep
that sounds very good and you know I've
been engaged with these licensing
standards for many years and I agree
with you that you know the current
models GPL is just strange and weird not
really practical for a lot of real-world
projects and yet on the other hand side
copyright is not what we're really
looking for for trying to build a world
around sharing I'm glad to learn about
you know new hybrid forms that have some
more critical thinking about real world
applications and then like I have to
check out fair shares that's real
interesting I tend to normally recommend
people look at the MIT licenses they
give you a lot of room to pretty much
dial in what you want and they're less
prescriptive than things like GPL it
might be that I don't know find out
maybe fair share just built on top of
the MIT licensing scheme but it's really
important and when people are gonna do a
project particularly in the non rival
wrist world I always tell them think
long and hard before you choose your
license because the license actually can
empower or can constrain what you're
trying to do yeah you know there's a
paradox right I mean if you define the
word communism like Marx did which means
everybody contributes what he wants and
uses what he needs that that was the
official definition in the 19th century
but you know before the totalitarian
Soviet systems changed the meaning if
you use that definition and
paradoxically you know the GPL is that
kind of license but then the paradox is
that it also allows big companies to use
that knowledge and so what you get then
is these open-source economies that are
totally dominated by a big companies now
it works for free software but what if
you start making these eyes for machines
right then you're really worried that
some big company will just take a design
and mass-produce that machine and they
will out-compete you in a matter of
months and you'll be dead you see what I
mean yep absolutely so in those cases
like for coops and singer I think the
idea of copy fair would really serve
their needs because then they could
share the knowledge but be secure that
it couldn't be used by
bad actors that just take the knowledge
and then you know destroy them in the
process so that's the kind of basic idea
it's it's you know it's a principle is
that yes knowledge can be shared but if
you make money you should you know share
a bit of it with all the people that
have co-created that knowledge that's
also the idea by the way I don't know if
you see that in my book but what we call
contributing accounting so I did a study
with a p2p Foundation and other
organizations in it was even before 2016
we had so we looked at 300 but we call
peer production communities and we found
that 75 percent of them so that's a
pretty high number were either
experimenting or already using
contribute if accounting so what that
means is if you have a commons community
you know you have all kinds of people
contributing but only if you are
actually able then to make money with it
and so it creates a question of equity
and fairness and so the idea then is
that you create is the second form of
accounting internally and so the money
comes in from the outside you have a
membrane in between and inside it's
redistributed in a different fashion
right and for example if you're
interested or your listeners are
interested they can look at the open
value system of cents Orica immemorial
which has been working for years on a
quite sophisticated system of
contributing accounting so it's
basically declaring that your community
you know can choose what is valuable for
your community and then especially now
that you have these intelligent you know
crypto monies you can actually design a
currency that reflects the value of your
community and so you have on the one
hand the cold currency if you like the
extractive currency and you can also
have your warm currency that represents
this kind of broader recognition of
collective value a very good point and
you know I like to point out to people
at least in the United States where I'm
very familiar with the internals of
corporate law you can actually do those
kinds of things within an ordinary
corporate
or LLC that's the one of the interesting
and odd things about English and
american-style law is that you can put
almost whatever you want in the bylaws
of a corporation as radical and
cooperative and a communitarian and
peer-to-peer as you want and it's just
really frankly a matter of imagination
and you don't have to go through the B
court process so that has some benefits
has no real legal significance it
basically takes the fact that we can do
this within the idea of law as code and
create what we want
I'll give you an interesting example of
something that we did that actually
touches back on something Michele spoke
about earlier the group of us started a
makerspace in the small city that I live
about an hour outside of and we ran it
nominally as a not-for-profit for about
two years but with the intent that it
would never be profitable and we would
plow the profits back into the
organization but it eventually got big
enough that we said well let's make it
clear that this will be a not-for-profit
forever so we we decided to go through
the paperwork of converting it to a
United States style not-for-profit and
get the tax authorities the IRS 401 C 3
designation so it could receive
tax-deductible gifts etc and then we
said how do we want it governed and we
jammed on it for awhile and one of the
people who jammed on it's extremely
creative young woman who's an anarchist
and another one who is a medievalist and
I who had some sympathy for both of
those but also knew a lot about you know
how to craft corporate organizational
forms and so we created what we call the
Council of guilds means of governance
and it's legal it's in our bylaws it was
approved by the state of Virginia and it
was approved by the US I RS as a legal
means to govern an entity and
essentially each of the skill areas at
our makerspace we have a very extensive
woodshop we have a pottery shop we have
laser cutters we have a bunch of 3d
printers we have digital Arts Center
each of those areas can organize itself
as a guild and they basically put one
person on the council of guilds which
from a legal perspective acts very much
like a board of directors would in a
normal corporation and there's a whole
mechanism for new
to be proposed and approved and such and
the Guild's are self-managing internally
within themselves people say how did you
do that I said easy it's just law as
code so one thing I would encourage
people who are thinking about doing
these things at least in the Anglo
sphere where we have the English common
law is to realize that a lot of these
very cool ideas can be done within the
old structures if you allow yourself a
blank piece of paper to design from I
I'm amazed that chip because I I didn't
know that and I I'd like to make a
little remark because so you know it's a
bit of a historical dynamic that I think
that was rushkoff also sometimes speaks
about this so basically you know once
you have kind of class society and and
and warfare and everything what an
empire does is it creates peace within
and war outside right it conquers and it
fights on the outside but in principle
you know you have like the Pax Romana
inside so the Middle Ages was a period
of time in Europe where there was no
central authority or very weak central
authority so this was a very distributed
system with no clear power and you have
you know here the church and the local
Lords and and then the cities came up
right and so that's very interesting
period because it shows you how a
distributive society can work you know
with competing power centers and and so
that's how the free medieval cities were
created when you know the the farmers
started leaving the countryside became
workers skilled workers and you know
created these Solidarity mechanisms
within the city and then also economic
ideas that were you know described in at
12 and 13th century but the thing is
that because the you know the elites
were always nostalgic of the Roman
Empire so when in the 16th century
you know everybody want to go back to
centralization right but now we are
exactly again in a period of time where
centralization is getting a very bad
reputation where we are kind of D
globalizing and so looking at the Middle
Ages becomes interesting
as a historical example of how things
can work in a distributed society so I'm
fascinated by the fact that you do that
and even call it kills because I've been
talking to some friends about this and
you know it's one of my ideas was we
have to look at how guilds worked not to
copy it you know point by point but that
is inspire us by you know prior
experience of people yeah that was our
thinking yeah I would love to get
material on what you're doing there this
is really interesting to me yet we'll do
it and I'll send you the link I will
post it on the episode page where we
actually actually send you the actual
legal document that we created to
instantiate our makerspace as a council
of guilds that it goes into quite a bit
of detail and the thing was it pass
legal muster at both the state and
federal levels so it's something people
can feel free to take and use we have
decided that as far as we're concerned
that intellectual work we did which was
quite a bit is in the Commons and
freedom for anyone to take and you know
we I don't if you know this Michael but
I've been involved from the very
beginning with a group called game B
that was one of the original game B team
and you know we've been thinking about
very similar things you're very very
similar things then and we do believe
that this current crisis is going to
open many ears to hear that perhaps you
know driving for the last penny of
economic efficiency by building this
world-spanning machine that's optimized
for short-term money on money return and
nothing else is not such a good idea and
then we're also looking back at some of
the older models right now we have some
folks looking into the kibbutz movement
in Israel for instance another one I've
looked into and in fact I look at my
bookshelf now I've got five books on the
topic are the Amish here in the United
States the Anabaptist German immigrants
who still to this day run an alternative
society embedded inside of American
society that has their own banking has
their own replacement for insurance by
religion they do not allow insurance but
they've created kind of a community will
take care of you rule that allow someone
to operate you know fairly risky
enterprises like farms without insurance
and they have a whole lot of things that
we can learn from
and we're amazed that these living
relics are still functioning and are
quite interesting as sources of material
take now I would not want to become
Amish thank you very much but some of
the ideas you know I'll give one example
you'll hear about the Amish you know not
using electricity or not using this or
not using that and they're not nearly as
black and white as you might think as it
turns out let's call it the broader
Amish and Mennonite community because
they're closely related all descended
from the German anabaptists there's a
group that's approximately like a parish
in more traditional Christian religion
that's you know 25 to 50 families that
is where the decision is made about what
technologies to use and how I'll give
you an example one form of old order
Mennonites that I know of they have
decided after a couple of years of
deliberation that it's okay to have
electricity in your barn so that you can
run milking machines for your cows and
refrigeration for the milk but it's not
okay to have electricity in the house
and again you know nuanced while other
groups of Mennonites say no electricity
or I'm Amish
typically will say no electricity at all
but sometimes while telephones right so
I can call the vet if the animals get
sick so they do it by deliberation at a
fairly local a quite local level you
know 25 to 50 families and you know
those ideas you know might actually be
interesting for our game be movement
that we could produce what we call per
Dobies which are small communities and
each one may be quite different I'd like
to give you another framing which I've
been thinking about so there's and you
know it's kind of related to what you
just said so the so the basic idea is
and it's called with a difficult world
wave those theory so these are
historians from different schools so you
have biophysical economics so that
people think about the economy in
thermodynamic ways your matter energy
flows you have Kaleo dynamics which is
kind of looking at rhythms in history
peter Turgeon and his school of
historians you have world Systems Theory
Palestine and and others Karl Polanyi
the double movement idea so different
ideas and here's the idea so
human history evolves between two
polarities of extraction and
regeneration and typically a class
society which competes with you know
other peers so nation states with
nation-states empires against the Empire
because they're in competition they will
overuse their resources not as an
exceptional thing but as a regular thing
and that's why you know historically all
civilizations that existed have
disappeared and so typically they do
distant to the point of collapse and
that arches in the pulse for the for a
period of regeneration and so my thesis
is that in these periods of regeneration
it's the commons that saves the day so
the Commons are used as a healing
mechanisms for societies and economies
which have overused their resources and
the principle of the Commons is
mutualization right so think about this
you have this highly predatory slave
based Roman Empire which becomes too
complex and start disintegrating and
what happens well what happens is the
Catholic monks you know mutual eyes
their life so they have food and shelter
and a rich spiritual life in a common
setting freely chosen they utilize their
knowledge because there wasn't copyright
and you know like the sister centers
which is one of those congregations that
was created by st. Bernard's they were
responsible 90% of the technological
innovation in the 11-12 centuries you
know there were the engineers of their
time right and then we localization of
the economy around the the feudal
domains so I think you can see what I'm
trying to say is that you know when
there is an overreach of a civilization
people go back to the Commons because
it's one of the ways to dramatically
lower the human footprint while actually
maintaining a good resource level and
you know psychologically let's say we
all have a fenced you know garden if I'm
unlucky I'm hungry you know what I mean
but if we have an agreement
the
you know there is some kind of
reciprocity mechanisms then you know
that if your garden doesn't function you
will still get what you need so this is
what the Commons are psychologically
right it's it's mutual eise's resources
so that there's a kind of insurance that
people can use it and I think so that
brings me back to you to your idea of
the image you know they came from these
periods where it was necessary to do
that and you know they have the really
symptoms being good enough so that it
could persist over these long periods of
time yeah it's quite amazing how and how
well they do I mean we have number of
Mennonites very close to us in fact our
county is now probably 10% Mennonite and
their farms are beautiful they take care
of their animals they take care of their
soil and they do a generation after
generation and they're able to live
within the game a world as we say in
game B and I know that's a very
important theme that we'll get to later
as we dig deeper into your book how
peer-to-peer Commons and other forms of
alternative organization can actually
embed itself within the current
structure at least for the time being
until working together we eventually all
erode it away right which is really an
important point let's stop here a little
bit and let's dig in a little bit more
into the idea of Commons we've touched
on it three or four times but we haven't
really flushed it out a lot this is very
important in fact I'm reading in bits
and pieces of time between my readings
for my podcast the book called free fair
and alive by a guy named David Boyer and
some other folks that really digs into
the concept of the Commons that I've
really become more interested in it that
before but anyway so I'll let you talk
about your vision of the Commons but one
thing that we'll have to put on the
table whenever Commons comes up you
certainly have to address Garret Hardin
and the idea of the tragedy of the
Commons and how you know that's not
nearer well anyway I'd love to hear your
view on that I have my view maybe I'll
speak after you're done yeah so the
ancient Romans already made a difference
between what they called res new use
what belongs to no one and it is
communists' what belongs to a you know
group of people or community and so
basically the mistake of Garrett Hardin
which he layer later on recognized is
that what he called the Commons were
actually not Commons with open access
resources so this is not you know like a
mountain flanking in the Swiss village
which is managed by the community but an
open area that everybody can use and
he's he's come it was right that open
access resources often lead to this
tragedy but it was mistaken to call it
the tragedy of the Commons because of
Commons by definition is governed to
exactly avoid that right so so he wasn't
really talking about Commons he was
talking about open fields that were from
no one and those are by definition not
Commons but open access resources so as
soon as people realize that that if they
do this selfish thing that you know the
resource will be the story they can make
agreements amongst each other to
preserve that resource and then it
actually becomes a Commons and then they
can preserve it over generations so
that's kind of the nuance and you know
I've seen that Gary Hart had actually
said that you know he apologized for
making a mistake because unfortunately
this mistaken you know kind of framing
became one of the key ideas of
neoliberalism and the idea that the only
thing that works is a private market so
they used his ideas to basically you
know go to war even more against the
Commons and that's a very sad thing and
this is still happening in Africa and
Asia and Ukraine you know where the
World Bank and the IMF are pushing this
idea everywhere of privatizing you know
these mutual resources and you know
often it doesn't work the way they
intend to do and and that's that's the
real problem I agree 100% with what you
said you hit it right on the nose that
people whip out Garrett Hardin like a
weapon sometimes right even though what
he was talking about was not anything
like the normal socially managed Commons
and of course we know Elinor Ostrom
actually got a Nobel Prize in part for
analysis of you know how Commons are and
ought to be managed and so there's a
very different regime they are manager
that what they're managed in a way that
isn't money on money returned capitalism
it's another one of these alternative
ways to do things may I mention one
difference I have potentially with the
book that you just mentioned and you
know I have to say you know these are
friends I work with them so we actually
part of the same group for a while which
was called the common strategies group
and so we David Bailey and silky
Helfrich the three of us we would
organize what we call deep dives and
these were like you know fairly
confidential meetings we would put two
groups of people together who didn't
know each other for example commoners
and and cooperatives or the commoners
and ethical finance and so we you know
we did that for a number of years to
create bridges between these various
communities but there's one point where
I think we differ and this is the the
notion of you know the relation between
the Commons and the market because I've
seen passages where they explicitly say
you know that there can be no relation
with the market I could be mistaken so I
would have to recheck it but okay
whether they say it or not I just want
to critique that position as long as you
say that Commons are only for volunteers
that cannot have any relation with the
market you know you put yourself in a
position where you don't have any
resources and you you are marginal and
what usually happens is that after five
or ten years the first generation is
exhausted and if they are not replaced
as the end of the project so I'm
actually for institutional redesign in
which you would think about the Commons
and then you think okay how can we
create ethical livelihoods so that our
Commons can persist over time I think
this is a very important time so first
at the micro level you know you have to
think about how do we do this for the
long term what kind of you know income
streams and to do that in a way that
doesn't endanger the comments right so I
call it reverse co-optation and I think
you mentioned Richard Bartlett and I was
it was before our recording but so which
aborted of we who is or used to be
within spiral which is a coalition of
coops and social entrepreneurs in New
Zealand you know they did something very
interesting which I call transvestite
so investment is using capital to
generate more capital transverse men is
using capital to create more comments
right you go you switch you transform it
from one value system to another and so
they took a million dollars to produce
loomio which is an open source free
software they guaranteed 5% return for
10 years but then they did a ritual to
give the resource to the Commons so this
is very interesting because at the same
time they satisfy the investor but by
really you know creating a wall between
their entity and the investment so there
they were not kind of in a slave-like
position to capital and at the same time
they created more comment so this is
something I described in the book is how
do we do what I call reverse co-optation
right so how do we protect ourselves as
commoners how do we maintain our ethics
and values and create equitable and fair
livelihoods without being overrun by
more predatory instincts this is the
problem that coops many times that right
coops have two big problems one is
called managerialism which is over time
there is an elite that becomes too
becomes managers and they don't really
involved all the memories anymore
but also what's called worker capitalism
which is yes you disability differently
but you're behaving the same as a
competitive firm and so my concern is
how do you avoid this how do you create
you know Commons that are in relation
with generative market functions so that
both can continue to exist in
equilibrium over a longer period of time
so that's what you'll find in my book it
is attempt to you know kind of do
institutional design so the commons
institution
market institution in the state
institution first of the micro-level
where you have the productive community
the intrapreneurial coalition nd what I
call the for benefit Association you
will note that most open-source projects
have some Association which manages the
infrastructure and the collaboration
infrastructure like in a Linux
Foundation Drupal Association and I
project it at the level of society so
can we imagine a society where civil
society is considered to be productive
because every citizen every inhabitant
actually contributes to the common good
and we recognize that can we have a
market that doesn't destroy communities
and natural resources and can we have an
enabling what I call a partner state
which creates the conditions that every
citizen can equally participate in this
contributory economy so that's kind of
my what I call post capitalist dream is
to have healthy markets healthy civil
societies and healthy state forms which
can create you know a bit what the image
do right is create long term stability
within planetary boundaries and we have
examples on a large scale and I recently
discovered this which is the Tokugawa
period in Japan which lasted I think two
to three centuries I'm not sure about
the timing but they have a balanced
economy with a stable population that
live within the regional planetary
boundaries of Japan so we know we can do
it and we know that we need the Commons
to really do this because actually what
happened was that the Emperor the Shogun
had taken over the land from these you
know rival feudal boards and and created
rules to avoid deforestation so that's
that's pretty interesting you know these
kinds of macro solutions that use the
Commons as a tool to maintain stable
societies yeah and I think what we just
talked about here and which as you say
is in your book and you give some good
examples in Chapter two which we'll get
to in a bit at least two of them that a
key question is not only long term but
also how do you get
there you know I was in my earlier days
a startup entrepreneur that I was an
investor in startups etc and one of the
rules I used for my own ventures and
investing in others and such is to
realize that nobody ever jumps up a
cliff right it just doesn't happen you
got to find a hill to walk up and you
know here we are surrounded on all sides
by this amazingly powerful
if stupid and brutal machine which we
call game a that is driven by money on
money return but also has a lot of
freedom in it and one of the freedoms is
to be able to build your own thing
inside of it and in fact in our game be
concept we're less doctrinaire about
commons per se that we do understand the
commons have to be a driving concept at
the highest level with respect to the
global systems but we are interested in
Commons we're interested in coops we're
interested in almost any kind of
organizational form that can make people
sovereign and be highly coherent and and
and here is the most important thing be
able to out-compete gamej entities at
least in some sectors because you can't
jump up a cliff we can't get to this
post capitalist world immediately and
probably the only roads there
immediately would be through violent
revolution where we're more likely to
end up with feudalism or neo-fascism
than we are what you and I want so we've
been thinking about how can we assure
that these entities are realistic and as
you say provide real livings for
themselves some of which may well be
engaging with game a at some level but
doing it in a way that you're able to
live true to yourself in a game B or
common or way and yet define those you
use the word membranes and I refine that
word a little further and call it semi
permeable membranes in the biological
realm every cell has a membrane but the
membrane has been designed by evolution
very carefully for what it both what's
in and what it puts out and so if we
think in terms of semi permeable
membranes being our operating entities
at around the Dunbar number or maybe
some collection of cells at the Dunbar
number that they have around them
be permeable membrane which is maybe we
make stuff to sell the game a world but
yet we live like game be one of the
examples I give just because it's so
absurd seemingly especially to white
people who come from the hippie-dippie
kind of point of view which is could you
want to imagine a game be auto repair
business right what you know fixing
those pollution belching demons
I go hey the world is full of auto
repair businesses and most of them are
very out or not most of them but many of
them are very unethical right they rip
people off they charge them for parts
they don't put in they buy cheap
knockoff parts from China and charge you
as if it was the ones from the original
car manufacturer it's a terrible
business most people have a catalogue of
abuse they've had at the hands of auto
repair so you know imagine a game B auto
repair business where we the people live
together in a physical community and and
govern themselves through a series of
rules and share their economics with
another set of algorithms but much of
the energy for the game be proto B which
is our lowest level of organization is
actually funded by our chain of auto
repair businesses that we all work in
and how do we out-compete what we have
compete by being ethical
by having worker management of the floor
I happen to have worked in the auto
business when I first got out of college
we'll probably why I know about this
example but within an auto repair
business there's horrible tension
rivalry and fighting between the service
writers are the ones who interface to
the customer and typically the ones
trying to rip you off and the workers
the mechanics the people who turn the
cranks who mostly want to do a good job
and then the parch department who's
always trying to pressure the mechanics
to buy as many parts as possible or get
in bed as many parts as possible and a
repair job whether it's necessary or not
you wonder why all they do these days is
just replace parts because it's the
parts department trying to muscle the
mechanics to do so
so our view is that or at least my view
I should say this is purely my crazy
idea is that if you were to organize
using game B principles in this very
game a business you'd out compete the
game a player's in your town very
quickly the word would get out Wow auto
repair business
totally ethical probably 10% cheaper and
they don't sell you crap you don't need
and you could use that economic profit
from the game a world to basically keep
the game be world going until gradually
we build our own economy and trade with
each other well you know what what
you're just saying is a bit what the
co-operative movement learned in 19th
century you know first they tried to
build productive co-ops but they they
didn't succeed because they couldn't get
the capital from banks and and and so so
they they kind of moved to consumer
coops and so what they decided and I
forgot the name of the Rochdale pioneers
right so they did they knew that they
could deliver food to the workers with
30% less than the private shops but they
also knew that if they did that they
would create so much animosity and they
would probably be destroyed so what they
did was give 10% discount a set of 30
and so they had 20% surplus that they
invested to grow the co-operative
movement and they were extremely
successful and I don't know if you know
this but there are more people today
working in co-ops are working for
multinationals and there's a study in
France showing their technical ops you
know have a 5-time less chance of going
bust and then the venture capital take
startups the problem is that people
don't know that right they don't know
that these things exist so in terms of
strategy I talked a lot about seed
Forbes right did the idea that when a
system is breaking down and so this is
the idea that we're now entering this
downward spiral you know if you remember
what I said in beginning this kind of
wave poles between extraction engine and
generative periods what campuses
achieved to do is to create an
extractive period which lasts it's very
very long and has culminated in a
globalized overuse so that's an
unpleasant situation because there is no
escape we've reached this overreach at a
global scale and so what happens in
these periods is that people look for
solution which obviously will not have
the same logic
the system that that is less and less
functioning and so this is what I call
seed form so for example you look at the
beginning of capitalism you know it took
eight centuries to prepare for four
modern capitalist society but it begins
with I'm sure you know that story but I
find it interesting is you know the
invention of purgatory right so you have
the Italian cities and at that time
usery was defined as just asking
interest so if you ask for interest you
go to hell so then they they because
there was a lot of pressure you know in
the Italian city-states they started
thinking about purgatory which is a very
convenient solution so they defined
lending interests no longer as a
cardinal sin but as a kind of moderate
sin and then you could buy back your sin
by buying indulgences which a church
used to in you know investing their cut
in their Gothic cathedrals and suddenly
Christians could lend money so that's
that's like an invention you know
pattern that would eventually enable the
capitals then you have double-entry book
account then you have the printing press
right so you could identify a number of
things that like existing seed confers
and they find each other and they create
organization which used two or three or
four or five of these patterns
eventually create a subsystem and
eventually that subsystems takes over so
this is the way I think that we are in
the period where we have to create seed
forms and look for niches where they're
viable and at the same time we work at
changing the rules of society so that we
can do this more and more right so what
you've done is hacking another example
you gave about the guild system but you
can also change legislation more radical
ways for example in Italy you know they
have the public Commons cooperation
protocols so that started in Bologna
actually it started with a
constitutional reform in which they
introduced the notion of subsidiarity so
that democracy should be done at the
lowest reasonable level and so no no
centralization wouldn't when it's not
necessary
and they use it in bologna to create a
rule that allows citizens to claim
something as a commons so you can say I
want to take care of the riverbeds I
want to rejuvenate this old factory
which is abandoned I want to wreak the
dynamized at the park and so this was so
successful Jim that it went to 250,000
cities and that now 1 million people are
doing urban Commons projects in Italian
cities so this is how you get from a
niche to a new norm does that make sense
I like it a lot yeah a couple of it
restricts earlier I did not know the
story that purgatory was a loophole for
letting money at interest I love that
actually yeah this is a bicycle a goof
if you're interested that he has a whole
book about that and I read it some years
ago quite easily but you know actually
more relevant today is this idea of you
know a seed starting in one place of
having the ability to find commons in
bologna and then having that spread
across all of italy that's the kind of
fan out i think we're both hoping that
our work will lead to overtime because
you have to have existence proofs i keep
coming back to this yeah yeah exactly
and I call this protocol cooperatives
and I let you speak that I want to
explain what that means okay that sounds
great yeah just a very short thing is
that one of my frustrations in some of
these social change groups is a whole
lot of people want to spend a whole lot
of time talking about theory which is
good I like theory I can go deep on
theory when I need to but to get beyond
the you know 1% elite thinkers of the
world you got to have existence proofs
they're not gonna take anybody's word
that some high concept way to redo the
world is gonna make life better for them
and their families you got to see it
work so I'm always looking for tangible
homey down-to-earth and preferably rival
risks examples of things that we can
actually show that our theories work and
I'm an empiricist if our theories turn
out not to work then there's something
wrong with our theories I'm completely
on your side on that and actually that's
what the p2p foundation does so we have
20,000 articles and concepts and
examples oh and
Rule two be in our wiki is that you have
to exist so the concepts I have are
considered are actually used by
communities that exist and the projects
that I use are not plans but they're
actually communities and project that
already exists you know sometimes they
exist in experimental form but they
exist you know what I mean
absolutely and we have to prototype we
have to experiment right and I build my
theory based on what I see in that
reality so that's really how I works
it's very close to what you're saying
yeah I love it
and I obviously knew about your work and
your foundation but I hadn't really dug
deep into it and one of the things that
I really love about doing my podcast I
do spend about 10 hours per episode
digging into people's materials the
amount of stuff I found on your wiki in
particular was holy moly I could spend a
month they get into that the other
resource of yours I'd call out to people
which I now follow it is you have a
daily blog post as well which is well
worth following and I had it written
down here where the hell is it it's
block doped p2p foundations of nets and
then we have Commons transitions org yep
so there's a huge amount of very useful
material which actually is our perfect
pivot to my next topic which is actually
from Chapter two in your book sort of
two parts to this first you talk about
value and what is value exchange value
versus use value like you get you talk
about that a little bit but then you you
dig into for examples and I'd be
particularly interested again my bias
towards tangible and how do we apply
these concepts to the rival risk domain
to the examples of wiki house and farm
hack okay yes so I I do want to say a
bit about value because I don't think I
talked about this and this is so
important so you know somewhere I think
in the 17th century we decided that
value could only be created in the
market so you need you know kind of a
commodity that you can sell on the
market and that creates value so to make
it simple you have three nurses one is a
volunteer for the mother teresa's
comfort congregation and
she's not counted anywhere in the GDP
she doesn't get a salary she doesn't
exist then you have a nurse that works
for a public hospital and she's come to
the cost so when there's an economic
crisis we spend too much the public
hospital will be closed and she loses a
job and then there's a third nurse and
she works a private hospital and she's
you know a positive force in our society
because she creates surplus value for
its shareholders so this is what the
value regime does you have three people
doing the same job and only one is
recognized as being a value creator
right and this is a big problem because
what it means is that we can only fund
regenerative activity in our society
either to taxation or philanthropy so
first we have to extract accumulate
profit and capital to our extraction and
then eventually you know we can invest
through taxation or philanthropy in
things that are good you know more
generative for the world and this is
this means that as long as we are in
this value regime we cannot structurally
solve our problems and so any real
change in civilizational paradigm is
also a change in value regime right just
to give another example you have the
Romans they have slaves work is for the
slaves work is not good a free person is
a person that doesn't work so that you
can you know dedicate its time to
philosophy and stuff that's the idea of
the ancient Greeks and the Romans then
the cretins come in and what they say is
no no no over at la bruja we have to
pray and work and work becomes a scene
as a way to bring in you know the divine
order in the Indian dear on the planet
Earth so you see that the medieval
system is actually a value revolution
compared to the Roman system right so
you have this kind and so what I'm
suggesting to you Jim is that we are
going to move from a commodity based
value system to a contribution based
value system and so that's absolutely
crucial so it we have to find mechanism
that allow us to do that and I want to
give you an example and this is from the
blockchain world right so maybe two
examples to make it a bit real one is
the idea of a shared public ledger to
directly finance generative work so the
example is tale data it's community
lanterns in France with 70 million
dollar capital they've proven already in
2016 that they saved the French state
300 million per euro per year in d
pollution costs so that the state
doesn't have to D pollute because they
don't pollute the water and the problem
is so today's we don't have any
mechanism to do this but imagine we have
a public ledger right like the
blockchain people are doing and so any
person could say here is the proof of my
decarbonisation effort right so you get
very fine and confirmed you get
tokenized and then either the state
decides is a priority or you go to the
institutions and companies that profit
from your positive externalities as they
call it and that way you have a direct
financing of generative work so this is
called circular Finance like the
circular economy need circular Finance
and what Weis is interesting because
what you can do is you can build in
limits like planetary boundary limits
and this is something called global
thresholds and allocations the group is
called reporting 3.0 so you have this
council that keeps track of all the
resources in the world and how much we
can use without destroying the planet
because you have all the freedoms but
not the freedom to destroy the planet
and we can integrate it in in our
accounting system so that people know
the choices that they have but within
that you are completely free you know to
solve your issues as you see fit as long
as you don't destroy go over the
planetary boundaries ok so I just wanted
to say this because this is very
important as the underlying you know
system that that I described in the book
so the two examples you were asking were
farm hack farm hack it Wiki house yes so
instead of harm hack
which I don't know very because that
that case that it was written by my
co-author there is a similar group in
France it's called attorney Basel so
what they do is they come together every
two weeks you know regional workshop and
they make a machine together right so
because their idea is that agribusiness
firms do not make the machines that is
more smaller family-oriented farmers
need so they will do it themselves and
so every two weeks they make a machine
that somebody needs in their network and
they will put the design in a global
Commons it's in French so that's a
limitation but you know they had like
2,000 designs already like three four
years ago and you know they have
hundreds of members and they are active
in the whole country of France so this
is a very interesting project that I
know a bit better and I think farm hack
is quite similar so these are just
people young farmers mostly that
basically create share designs of things
they need in their work and you know
they hack farm machinery because I'm
sure you know this right if you buy a
John Deere tractor it's illegal to
repair it because you sign a contract
which includes the software on the
machine and its private software and
you're not allowed to change it you know
so this creates kind of a new feudalism
that's what these groups kind of you
know act against Sawicki house I know a
bit better because I've visited them in
New Zealand and basically they want to
make a zero carbon positive I think it's
called a house and again the idea is to
work together in community and to share
the design globally so that if they're
successful other people can simply then
you know copy the design and do it in
another locality may be adapted and so I
come back to I wanted to say before you
you told your story this is what I call
a protocol cooperative so what is the
protocol cooperative you know it's it's
creating joint patterns so that the
whole ecosystem can organize themselves
around this joint patterns if you
remember occupy was like that right now
occupy has had you know ultimately
failed had weakness
but it did succeed in very rapidly
mobilizing a huge number of people like
15m in in Spain was like 1 million
people on the streets because they had a
common protocol like if you do this and
this and this you can call yourself
occupied and wiki houses the same if you
do this and this and this you can call
yourself wiki house and then you can
also participate in the system and so we
go from economics of scale which is what
we do now which is by producing more of
a single unit you can make it cheaper
but it also means you're using more
energy and resources in order to obtain
that competitivity and you go to another
model which is called the economies of
scope which is doing more with less so
basically on the information level what
happens is in a system like that
any innovation anywhere in the world can
be copied very rapidly by anybody else
in the ecosystem so you can imagine
ultimately the what's it's called open
motors does that that you have you know
designs for cars and if a local city
decide we're gonna make our own buses
they don't necessarily have to buy it
from a big private company they can say
we can make our local biodegradable you
know renewable buses based on modular
repairable systems we can make them
right here and this is what I call
Cozumel local production where
everything that is lights is global and
shared and everything that is heavy is
low like that a lot in fact I'm going to
point this one out the wiki has one to
our game be community for people to dig
into because there are groups getting
ready to actually create communities
physical ones and one of the things that
people are talking about is what are
economic and ethical ways to build good
housing and it looks like this wiki
house is quite an interesting concept
yes I have a whole category of a housing
you know category housing in my wikis so
you'll see this there's a lot more and
so that's that's really what I want to
push is that people have to know these
nice seed forms so they
learn from each other and we have a big
problem which is fragmentation which is
that you know I went to Tuscany and
there were 13 pieces of software to
order organic food from CSAs
community support agriculture that's
insane you know we have two mutual eyes
our knowledge and in open sewers you can
still adapt it to your local situation
but you have this core commonality so
that we don't have to reinvent the wheel
because that's the problem when we
compete with capitalism right if they
can make an uber which is you know
globally scale based on one pattern and
you are you know redesigning you know
ten thousand different places something
different you hug how are you going to
compete very good point though of course
in a weird way you bir use your strategy
they did that which is light and did it
globally the software and that which is
heavy the car and made their drivers pay
for the cars so they didn't have any
capital costs yeah brilliant and in hey
that predatory about predatory you know
unfortunately anything good can be used
for bad which actually gives us a
perfect transition to the the next topic
and I guess it'll be probably the last
topic because we're kind of getting
short on time got a lot of other
interesting things to talk about in my
notes maybe be interested in coming back
for a part two I do this fairly often
yeah I'd like to I'd like to because
yeah you're right there's a lot to
discuss and I think also for people you
know it can be too long because there's
a lot to to digest actually ok let's go
on one on the last topic that we have
time for and then we'll have you back
for a part two to get into a whole bunch
of other things and that is your that
you talked about quite a bit in Chapter
three of the period of here book which
is how are many too many communications
and other things that we are creating in
this internet world of ours provide us
what you called new socio technological
frameworks why don't we talk about that
a little bit then I'll probably follow
up on that because that's the area I did
most of my business career in right well
so last year produced also another
report I want to briefly mention it's
called p2p accounting for planet to
survival
so I proposed a kind of unified global
infrastructure to produce for human
needs within planetary boundaries and I
have one slide that maybe we can talk
about it next time I just want to
mention it because people believe
technology is neutral that you know you
can make some invent something and then
depends how you use it
and I'm thinking this is not exactly
true because the way you design
something is already value driven and
you can see that with the internet right
it starts in the army where the
noncommissioned officers are telling
their officers
we need a distributed system because
when you know when when the headquarters
will be bombed in the world and we can't
do anything anymore
so DARPA develops this idea and then
scientists start cheating and you know
introducing the Internet in their
offices you know there's a story about
actually making a cable you know without
permission so the scientists take it
over and then the students and the
researchers in the academia right and
then you have the browser and then the
people come in and once the people are
there the businesses then come in and
they change the internet into organic
client-server logic they go away from
the peer to peer because they can't
control it and then the third wave is
government see that happening so oh my
god we need to control this and they you
know then surveillance is introduced so
I just want to say that design
technology is not neutral
it's a based on values and on values and
design decisions and so you apply that
to peer to peer and what I described in
chapter 3 is that there are now four
competing models because peer to peer is
here to stay it's kind of the basic
paradigm but then how you implement it
is based on values interests etc so you
have a quadrant with centralized and
global versus local and distributed and
you have another line your result a line
between for profit and for benefit so
centralized for profit peer-to-peer what
does that mean well that's Facebook
uber and Google so they allow us to do
peer-to-peer on their platforms but
everything in the background is
privatized and so our data becomes a new
oil and they sell our attention so I
call this net article capitalism because
it's the hierarchy of the network but
you know they still they still enable a
lot of peer-to-peer you know even though
we might criticize them and I do but you
know for example Facebook in Austin in
Belgium because I'm originally from
there you know there's a community
fishing project where the consumers
ordered the fish directly from the
fishermen and then pick them up when
they come from back from the sea yeah
that's a very positive communities for
the fisheries that is actually managed
to true Facebook right then the second
distributed for profit is basically what
I call the blockchain world so they use
things like proof of work and what's the
other name proof of stake they're all
oligarchic protocols I'm sorry these are
protocols which give more to the people
who already have more so you look at the
distribution of Bitcoin it's more
unequal than sovereign right on the
other hand these people are doing you
know great innovations they're creating
open collaborative systems they reserve
40% of the tokens for the workers you
know there's some really interested
interesting stuff happening there and
now we're moving to post blockchain
Ledger's so that's I think very
interesting then on the on the other
side of this gradient you have two other
modes one is what I call urban common so
local projects small open locally
connected SLOC and there's you know this
is what I think I told you that for
example in Ghent in Belgium we went from
50 urban Commons to 500 in ten years so
this is also happening and then the
global Commons ID is the last one for
example I think that cities should
create leagues like in the Middle Ages
and create protocol coops for every
provisioning system that needs to be
visualized in the city so shared habitat
mobility shared food and it's absolutely
horrendous that you know the
should happen independently in every
city when they could actually create a
core of patterns that could be used by
all the petition so this is a way to
actually deceive a form of trans local
the transnational governance where the
city becomes the tool of global
governance right in alliance with
ethical finds and coops and whatever
anyone lies with these communities that
produce the code and use the
capabilities of these infrastructures so
I hope that's a bit clear so what I'm
saying is they are developing all four
at the same time in competing with each
other
and right now of course the new tactical
side is winning and dominant but they
are actually very predatory system so I
don't think they are a lot they're
sustainable in the long term right
Airbnb destroys the inner city it chases
people away
uber produces more pollution rather than
less so there are fundamental issues
with these models which are
fundamentally predatory and they don't
pay taxes and they don't invest in
infrastructure use you know for socially
paid for by their own workers so these
are very problematic models absolutely
it is interesting that there are a few
upstarts against uber I know in Austin
Texas there's a local I think it's a
driver own co-op that has almost 50
percent of the market but you know the
talk of all these csa software platforms
there somehow need to be a global level
of standardization templates or seeds as
you call them or we call them the game
be world X in a box essentially a
turnkey how can anyone anywhere set up a
goober coop essentially and that seems
to be how at least one way that we could
nip away at these kind of over
concentrated network predators yeah
I I completely so we have to start with
seeds you know then become niches and
then add some more when Tunisia's to
become the norm and we know this can
happen because you think about Germany
and renewable energy right so you have
this one village co-op for maybe 20
years ago
and they have to fight for five years to
have the legal right to form renewable
energy co-op so once it's accepted by
the legal system it starts proliferating
but it never goes more than a two three
percent of energy production but then
you have Fukushima and the Greens are in
the government that they made a deal
with Merkel and then they introduced a
feed-in tariffs and within five to seven
years 62% of the energy market is you
know done by these village coops so
that's in that niche they have one you
know what I mean
it's of course it's good enough but if
you think of the emergence of capitalism
you know it took a very long time for
them to become the law now we don't have
eight centuries that's for sure so we're
gonna have to be you know working
accelerated ways but also the I I don't
find a reference to this but so many
told me is that we are learning eight
times faster than like 30 years ago
right so the the the fact that we have
the internet needs collective
intelligence means that innovations are
now moving so rapidly think about
permaculture that went from nothing to
my with thousands and thousands upon
thousands of projects also of course in
a bad way I read another article about
bombs that you can make you know side on
the side ways like in Afghanistan they
took them six months to make to learn
about this and now it's like two weeks
so this is at the same time I hope
because even though we can do bad things
with it it means that because we're
gonna accelerate it decline we also have
to learn much more rapidly what the
alternatives are so this is going to be
in some way again a race against time
and can I tell you one more thing Jim
before we end this
so Peter Pagani has a book called
rethinking in the world and I think it's
very important so he says okay Society
is a complex adaptive system so it
doesn't change because good people
decide to do things differently it
changes because a system breaks down
creates a chaotic transition with the
perforation so global system zero
forum is a merchant captain system
before 1789 it's interrupted by the
chaotic transition of the French
Revolution and the Napoleonic Wars 1815
creates global system one which is
industrial capitalism but it's a full
domination of capital over labor that is
interrupted by World War one and World
War two which creates global system to
the welfare state model which broke down
in 2008 so we are now in the care of the
transition and you take them Peter
Turchin who wrote an article you know
following his rhythms that I explained
in the beginning he predicted that we
would have a cascade in the 20s and it's
actually happening with Kovac right so
his ideas that we now have ten years of
downward spiraling with enormous amount
of social strife and you know it starts
in the US with with the George Floyd
mobilizations he says usually after 10
years elites get tired and starts you
know being more willing to introduce
reforms I think that's an interesting
way to know where we are you know what I
mean it really is it really is a road
map for where we are and then what you
talked about earlier but within the
constraint of the fact that this road
map has to be accelerated we don't have
a century to make each transition
exactly exactly and I noticed that you
actually have a collaborator that we
share which is Daniel 'shmock converger
who's also a key contributor into the
game be work released it's not know he's
on the p2p foundation but you know we
communicate occasionally so yeah I
wouldn't call him a collaborator but I I
you know I do follow his work and I you
know I watched the rebel wisdom tapes
because you know his capacity to think
about complexity is very deep and I I
don't have that but I think I don't know
if he's done this but you know what I'm
proposing is also to have a sense of the
pulse of time right not just to know
where we are but when we are and I don't
and I don't do this to tell people you
know this is a deterministic future it's
gonna come out of melody but I think it
can help
to position yourself in okay now we we
going for difficult time so let's
prepare for what comes next
right now is the time the seed forms
indeed well on that I think we will wrap
it up this has been extraordinarily
interesting I knew it would be after
having done my research and we've left a
lot on the table particularly talking
about the transition strategies and how
b2b in the Commons need the you know
couple with governance law intelligence
infrastructure and indeed values and
coherence and we'll do a part two and
get into those so I like to really thank
you Michelle for an incredibly deep and
interesting episode thank you so much
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
Jared Jane's consulting music by Tom
Muller at modern space music com